<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The repaire of honour, falsely impeached by Featlye a minister Wherein (by occasion) the apostles disciple S. Ignatius Bishop &amp; martyr, his religion, against Protestantisme, is layd open. By Ed. Weston Doctour of Theology: in a letter, by him written vnto two fathers of the Society of Iesvs, in England.</title>
            <author>Weston, Edward, 1566-1635.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14979</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25289</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101852</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837655</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837655</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1993</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14979)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1993)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1016:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The repaire of honour, falsely impeached by Featlye a minister Wherein (by occasion) the apostles disciple S. Ignatius Bishop &amp; martyr, his religion, against Protestantisme, is layd open. By Ed. Weston Doctour of Theology: in a letter, by him written vnto two fathers of the Society of Iesvs, in England.</title>
                  <author>Weston, Edward, 1566-1635.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by the English College Press],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at Bruges [i.e. Saint-Omer :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Actual place of publication and press from STC.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: Featley, Daniel.  The Romish fisher caught and held in his own net.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Featley, Daniel, 1582-1645 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Jesuits --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1993:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1993:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE REPAIRE OF HONOVR, Falſely impeached by <hi>Featlye</hi> a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter. Wherein (by occaſion) the Apoſtles Diſciple <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> Bishop &amp; Martyr, his Religion, againſt Proteſtantiſme, is layd open.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Ed. Weſton</hi> Doctour of Theology: In a Letter, by him written vnto two Fathers of the Society of IESVS, in England.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>Imprinted at Bruges. ANNO 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:1993:2"/>
            <head>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>ERY REVEREND FATHERS</head>
            <p>I moſt hartily ſalute your perſons, and alſo ioyfully congratulate you, in regard of your pious and charitable indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours there in England, for the cauſe and right of the Catholike Church. Neither neede I, your knowne zeale conſidered, by letters to encourage you to labour in that kind, or with vndauſited mindes va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liantly to beare the ſlaunders &amp; falſe reports of the common aduerſary: Seing that as one you imbrace, ſo the other you may iuſtly contemne, &amp; with great reaſon reioyce in both.</p>
            <p>The cauſe at this preſent, of my wryting vnto you, hath beene oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned by one <hi>Featlye</hi> a Miniſter-Doctour: who by a diuulged Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet in print, hath raiſed a ſcandall with you, out of a report of the <hi>Earle</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:1993:2"/> of <hi>VVarwicke,</hi> made of me concorning ſome words I vttered vnto him, at ſuch time as hee was heere in <hi>Bruges. Featlye</hi> then auoucheth to the world, that the ſaide <hi>Earle</hi> tould him, that I talking of a diſputation in London, paſſed betwixt you, and a couple of Miniſters <hi>VVhite</hi> &amp; <hi>Featlye,</hi> affirmed, that in regard the actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by you, and baſely by them, two English Earles preſent at your diſpute, thereby to haue beene co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Catholike fayth. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Featlye,</hi> as I am tould, both to the preiudice of my perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; reproach of the Catholike cauſe, hath in print auouched, that wee by no other meanes maintaine our quarrel againſt them, then by lyes &amp; falſe inuentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. I haue therfore thought it conuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in few words to expreſſe the truth; &amp; alſo to craue your aſſiſtance, that by your meanes the ſame may appeare to confront, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>found the ſla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derer.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:1993:3"/>
            <p>Concerning then the report of the Earle and <hi>Featlye,</hi> I proteſt vnto you, and to the world, vpon the word of a Prieſt, that for the preſent I cannot call to mind any ſuch words I vttered vnto the ſaid Earle: yet do I not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely affirme, that I ſpake the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not. But this I ſay for a certainty; that if <hi>I</hi> tould him any ſuch thing, withall I added; that ſuch a bruite was repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to mee by ſome, that came out of England, and paſſed by mee heere in <hi>Bruges.</hi> Which particularity, as it ſeemeth to me, should haue beene ſpecified to <hi>Featlye</hi> by my Lord, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the quality of that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Eſtate he pretendeth.</p>
            <p>Wherevpon I affirme, that the dealing of <hi>Featlye</hi> towards mee, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I vtterly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temne it, to haue beene childish, vnciuill, &amp; no ſmall demonſtrance of the greate weaknes of his Religion, conſtrayned, againſt good manners &amp; ſubſtance of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1993:3"/> to lay hould vpon ſuch toyes, &amp; meere aeriall babblements. Which my contempt of ſuch dealing, the world should know by my ſilence, if the good of others, impeached by his ſca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dall, did not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d mee to ſpeake.</p>
            <p>Suppoſall the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be, that I made ſuch a relation to the Earle of <hi>VVarwicke;</hi> what ground, or good occaſion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth thence to argue againſt mee, or againſt Catholiks? If I had beene in London at ſuch time as the diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation was performed, where I might haue beene informed concerning the truth in all points, then I might haue beene in ſome shew blamable, if I had vented forth ſuch a thing; but being in <hi>Bruges,</hi> &amp; ſpeaking familiarly to my Lord, what I heard from paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers out of England, there is no appearance of any euill carriage on my part, or any ſiniſtrous meaning to diſgrace eyther <hi>Featlye,</hi> or any of his faction. But ſomething they muſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1993:4"/> ſay to ſtoppe vp the gappe, &amp; breach of their cauſe, made by our battery, at leaſt to the eares of the ſimple, &amp; eaſily deceaueable popularity.</p>
            <p>Aſſuredly it is not the practice of our Profeſſours to make lyes, to raiſe ſlaunders for our defence, or thereby to impugne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for our argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts to that effect are copious, pregna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; in the view of the beſt intellige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Rather it is the Proteſtant, being in affection furious, in iudgment ſuperficiall, to inuent &amp; blaze out lyes, and that in print, to iuſtifie themſelues, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peach vs. Let them to this effect take only a view of the lyes, cauils, falſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, diſcouered of late in the writings only of <hi>Hall,</hi> and <hi>Collins,</hi> by Fa. <hi>Coffin</hi> and Fa. <hi>Fitzherbert,</hi> and they shall in their beſt iudgements, confeſſe them guilty, impudent, moreouer diſgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to the ſyncerity of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, yea and to mankind. What a villany was it for one of that crew to print, that in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:1993:4"/> 
               <hi>Antwerp</hi> he ſaw a Prieſt ſaying Maſſe in the sha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bles, &amp; that in the ſame place where the Butcher made his ſlaughter, framing blaſphemouſly an <hi>Antitheſis</hi> betwixt the Prieſt, and the Butcher?</p>
            <p>But if aduantages be to be made abſolutely vpon reports, doubtleſſe then in this very preſent Caſe we haue much for vs. I haue heard heere in this Citty, from the mouthes of many English lately come from En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, that you both were ſo eneom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred by the Miniſters in diſputation, that you had not a word to ſay for your defence. Which report muſt needes bee moſt falſe, both your worthes in learning conſidered, and alſo the quality of the argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, then put in diſpute, examined. For what had you otherwiſe to doe, but out of the Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtory to repeate the auncient and continued profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Catholike Roman fayth, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Apoſtles tymes to our dayes:
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1993:5"/> and out of the ſame Hiſtories to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of your Aduerſaries a like reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall of age, and continuance, for the profeſſion of their Proteſtantish Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion? in which matter what could bee wanting for you, or ſufficient for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? No Hiſtory recordeth, euer any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Eccleſiaſticall or ſecular ſince the Apoſtles dayes, to haue accorded in all poynts with <hi>Luther &amp; Caluin.</hi> Onely this they may ſay; That what they maintayne now againſt vs, they lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it of <hi>Manichaeus,</hi> of <hi>Heluidius,</hi> of <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilantius,</hi> of <hi>Image-breakers,</hi> of <hi>Beringa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> of <hi>VVickcliffe,</hi> of <hi>Huſſe,</hi> &amp; ſuch like condemned baggages by the Church of God. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was it moſt ſlaunderous, what was diuulged by Proteſtants, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning your fayle in diſputation.</p>
            <p>Now then, ſeing it hath pleaſed <hi>Featlye</hi> to work a feate againſt vs, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of things miſreported, I shall come neere vnto his owne perſon, not vpon the maintenance
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:1993:5"/> that rumours and news may affoard, but vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that which wee may ſuppoſe hee hath printed by himſelfe, or his friends. I would then haue him vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that I haue ſeene a Pa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>phlet ſet out, purporting the iſſue of the diſputation hee had with you. And aſſuredly I neuer in all my life beheld a more liuely repreſentation of a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters folly, short ſight, and ſleight braines, then therein. Wherefore to omit how according to his owne fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulatory Relatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it is moſt manifeſt, that ſtill hee flieth from the ſtate of the queſtion, and wholly refuſeth to make an abſolute Catalogue of men, ſince the Apoſtles dayes, profeſſing his Religion, accordingly as you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of him; I charge him with the aſſertion of two moſt notorious lyes, made to iuſtifie his cauſe.</p>
            <p>The former conſiſteth in this, that hee rehearſeth. you to haue beene doubtfull, poſitiuely to affirme, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1993:6"/> our Sauiour Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles were Authours of Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy or no, and there vpon to haue refuſed to make a demurre with him about their writings for the tryall. The falſity of which report is moſt euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. For how can a Catholicke bee vnſetled for ſuch a reſolution? Hee then might haue perceaued the cauſe, if hee had beene ſyncere, why you would hee should paſſe from Chriſt &amp; his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles downeward to enſuing Paſtours and Doctors in the Church, that hee being not interrupted, might haue leaue more freely to ſpin out the threed of his rehearfall, concerning the ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Profeſſors of his Religion. Neither according to prudence, and the ſtate of the Queſtion, ought you to haue made ſtay about the writings of the new Teſtament. Firſt for that all Heretickes, which euer haue beene, haue challenged thoſe ſacred Records in approuance of their He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1993:6"/> doctrines. Then, for that, if you had made ſtay about them, your principall intent had beene fruſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: &amp; ſo the Aduerſary should haue beene imployed in ſuch ſort about in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter pretations of the new Teſtament, and diſcuſſion of ſeuerall controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies therein expreſſed, that he should neuer haue had leaſure for the decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the enſuing viſible profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for times following thoſe of the Apoſtles. And ſo with a lye, and a Calummation hath hee flatly iniured you in this point.</p>
            <p>The ſecond notorious lye of his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth in this, that hee produceth <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> Bishop of Antioch, and Martyr in Rome, for a Proteſtant, or a Puritane; which lye is ſo shamefull a thing in the view of all learned me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that <hi>Featlye,</hi> although aſſiſted with the writings of a Geneuian Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tishman, yet hee shall neuer be able to make any colour to hide,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1993:7"/> or excuſe the impudent falſity ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Wherefore he is to vnderſtand from mee, that as I herein giue him the Lye;ſo the ſame is to lye heauily, &amp; diſgraciouſly vpon him, vntill hee proue theſe ſeueralties of doctrine. Firſt, that S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> with Proteſtants or Puritans taught, that one not cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led &amp; conſecrated by the Paſtors of the Preſent Church, or preaching co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary doctrine vnto theirs, may bee a competent Miniſter of the Word &amp; Sacraments, Secondly, that Kings or Queenes bee ſoueraigne in Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall affayres. Thirdly, that the Hierarchy of the Roman Church, conſiſting of Bishops, Prieſtes, Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, Subdeacons, Exorciſts, Aco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytes, and others, is not allowable. Fourthly, that all traditions not writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten concerning fayth or Religion are ſuperſtitious. Fifthly, That in the Church of God, there is neyther Prieſthood nor Sacrifice. Sixtly,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:1993:7"/> that the holy <hi>Euchariſt</hi> is nothing els but repreſetatiue bread &amp; drinke. Seauenthly, that wowed eſtate of Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginity, in Religious perſons, is repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnant to the liberty of the Ghoſpell. Eightly, that preſcribed faſts of Lent and fryday haue no obligation. Nin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thly, that one Vertue is not more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, or meritorious in Gods ſight, then another. Tenthly, that Sinnes by Iuſtification are not abolished, but onely not imputed, although they remaine in the ſoule Eleue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>thly, that Saintes in their owne Perſons, or Reliques are not to bee worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped. Twelfthly, that God is authour of Sin, ordayning the ſame, as effects of neceſſity, in the will of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Laſtly, that <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> held a different fayth from <hi>S. Policarp,</hi> from <hi>S. Iuſtin</hi> Martyr, from <hi>S. Irenaeus,</hi> from <hi>S. Chryſoſtome,</hi> from <hi>S. Auguſtine,</hi> and <hi>S. Gregory</hi> the great. But if in all theſe points wee may finde this renowned Bishop and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1993:8"/> Martyr within the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe onely of a few Epiſtles wholly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtantiſme, and conformable to the preſent doctrine and practize of the Catholick Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Church, eſpecially conſidering that for his ancietry, he might well haue ſeene <hi>S. Iohn Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt,</hi> for his profeſſion in worke &amp; wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, as recordeth <hi>Euſebius lib. 5. hiſt. ca.</hi> 36. to haue induſtriouſly recorded the <hi>Traditions of the Apoſtles;</hi> it muſt enſue thereon, that the authority of ſuch a man, in matter of Religion, as it is in it ſelfe moſt graue &amp; waighty; ſo alſo powerfull and irrefragable for vs againſt Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>To examine then the aforeſayd points of doctrine concerning Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, whether in fauour of Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts they be determined by <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> or no, wee will begyn the tryall in order from the firſt S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> then <hi>epiſt. ad Trallian.</hi> when hee had made men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Paſtors, who gouerne in the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1993:8"/> Church, as of Bishops, of Prieſts, of Deacons, thus concludeth: <hi>Quligitur his non obedit, Atheus, &amp; impurus eſt, &amp; Chriſtum contemnit, &amp; conſtitutionem eius imminuit VVhoſoeuer doth not obey theſe, he is an Atheiſt, he is impure, he contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth Chriſt, &amp; impaireth his ordinance</hi> By the Judgment then of S. <hi>Ignatius, Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> and <hi>Caluin</hi> were Atheiſts, they were contemners of Chriſt his Law, in that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they firſt bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched a doctrine wholly contrary to the doctrine of all the knowne Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors in Chriſt his Church then li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, or gouerning in the ſame, for fourteene hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred yeares before. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are all Proteſtants reprooued by S. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> who teach, that it is lawfull to preach a doctrine by the priuate ſpirit, iudged conformable to the Scriptures, although diſcorda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t from all preſent Bishops, Prieſtes or Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons now therein, or for the time paſt hauing borne rule in the ſame.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:1993:9"/>
            <p>The ſecond point importeth <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy</hi> in Churchly affayres, of which thus <hi>S. Ignatius ep. ad Magneſ. &amp; Philadel. Principes obediunt Caeſari, milites Principibus, Diaconi Presbyteris ſacrorum praefectis: Presbyteri, Diaconi, &amp; reliquus Clerus, vnâ cum populo vniuerſo, militibus, principibus, &amp; Caeſare, ipſi Epiſcopo pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reant: Epiſcopus Chriſto, &amp; Chriſtus Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tri. Princes obey Caeſar, Souldiers the Princes, Deacons Prieſts, as Prefects ouer holy myſteries; Prieſtes, Deacons, the whole Cleargie, togeather with all the people, as Souldiers, Princes, and Caeſar, are to obey the Bishop: the Bishop is to obey Chriſt, &amp; Chriſt his Father.</hi> Then as <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> ſubiecteth the whole Laity to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop, ſo reſolueth he the Supremacy in the Bishop only vnto Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The third poynt implieth the <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> or <hi>Hierarchy</hi> of the Church in her Paſtors and ſacred officers: and is by <hi>S. Ignatius ep. ad Magneſ. &amp; Antiochen.</hi> deſcribed, where hee maketh men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1993:9"/> of Bishops, of Deacons, Subdea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, of Readers, of Oſtiarij, of Exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſts. And is this face of a Church then, in her Apoſtolicall prime, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to the preſent Proteſtants Churches in their pretended refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of England, of Scotland, of Holland, of France, of Geneua?</p>
            <p>The fourth point, touching <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions,</hi> appertayning to Fayth &amp; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, is thus diſcuſſed by S. <hi>Ignatius Ep ad Magnefianos. Audiui quoſdam dicen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes: Niſi Euangelium inuenero in archiuis, non credo. Talibus ego dico, quod Ieſus mihi pro archiuis eſt. I have heard ſome ſay: vnles I find the Ghoſpell in place of Records, I will not beleeue. To ſuch</hi> I <hi>ſay, that Ieſus to me is in place of all ſuch places of Records.</hi> Where hee ſayth, that our Sauiour Chriſt hath taught his Church not onely the Written word of the Ghoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, but alſo by traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of himſelfe, and of his Apoſtles. Wherevpon <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius</hi> teſtifieth, that <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> did
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:1993:10"/> much labour to lay downe the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of the Apoſtles <hi>lib. 3. Hiſt. Cap. 30.</hi> How then do Proteſtants agree with <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> reuoking all matters of fayth to the written Letter of the Scriptures, expounded by themſelues in ſeuerall?</p>
            <p>The fifth poynt appertayneth to <hi>Prieſthood</hi> and <hi>Sacrifice. Saint Ignatius</hi> maketh oftentimes mention of Prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſthood in the Euangelicall Law, <hi>Ep. ad Trallian. &amp; ad Magneſian.</hi> but the Proteſtants diſclaime fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Prieſthood as they doe from Sacrifice. A ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous thing to ſay, that to preach, to giue memorials of Chriſt, to baptize is to exerciſe the office of a Prieſt, in that Prieſthood importeth an office to ſacrifice. Whervpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many learned Proteſtants affirme, that in the new lawe no Prieſthood is to bee found. Likewiſe the ſame <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> maketh mention of Altars <hi>Epiſt ad Magneſian. Omnes velut vnus quiſpiam ad templum</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:1993:10"/> 
               <hi>Dei concurrite, velut ad vnum Altare. All you as one perſon go togeather to the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, as to one Altar.</hi> But this word <hi>Altar</hi> hath a relation to a Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice: whereas bread and wine with Proteſtants reſpect a <hi>Communion Table,</hi> not an <hi>Altar.</hi> What needeth an Altar for one taking bread, to think with himſelf, that as bread nourisheth the body, ſo doth Chriſt the ſoule. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>revpon if Turks were Proteſtants, they were to eate and drinke their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Carpets ſpread vpon the ground or pauement, not at any reſemblance of an Altar. If they ſay that the Table according to our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours inſtitution be of a diuine In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, they are to vnderſtand, that the Table did principally reſpect the Supper and Paſchall Lambe, not the holy Euchariſt to which belonged an Altar, not a Table. Prieſthood then, and Altars mentioned by <hi>S. Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius</hi> ouerthrowe Proteſtancy.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:1993:11"/>
            <p>The ſixt poynt concerneth the holy <hi>Sacrament of the Altar,</hi> of which <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> ep. <hi>ad Romanos,</hi> thus ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth. <hi>Panem Dei volo, panem caelestem, quae est caro Chriſtifilij Dei. Ep. ad Smir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſ.</hi> (cited by <hi>Theodoret dial. 3.) Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charistiam &amp; oblationes non admittunt, quod non confiteantur Eucharistiam eſſe carnem Saluatoris nostri Ieſu Christi. I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the bread of God, that heauenly bread which is the flesh of Chriſt the Sonne of God. They allow not oblations, for that they will not confeſſe the Eucharist to bee the flesh of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein if hee had deemed, that onely bread was to bee found as Proteſtants do, he had not fliled it, <hi>the flesh of Chriſt;</hi> neither should he haue had any iuſt reaſon to rebuke thoſe Heretiks in ſuch tearmes as hee doth.</p>
            <p>The ſeauenth point appertayneth vnto religious <hi>Viginity,</hi> of which thus hee writeth <hi>Ep. ad Philadel. Vxores Maritis ſubditae ſint in timore Dei, Virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1993:11"/> Chriſto in puritate, non abhominantes nuptias, ſed id quod Praeſtantius eſt ample<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctentes. Let wiues be ſubiect to their Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sbands in the feare of God, Virgins to Christ in purity, not deteſting marriage, but imbracing that which is more excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</hi> Firſt then againſt Proteſtants haue we, by the Record of <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> practice of vowed Virginity; in regard whereof the ſame <hi>S. Ignatius Ep. ad Smirnenſ.</hi> ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luteth <hi>Virgins that liue in perpetuall vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginity,</hi> which eſtate of perpetual virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, for that it implyed a vow, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vnto it hee requireth Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Bishop: <hi>Siidipſum ſtatuatur ſine Epiſcopo, corruptum est:</hi> If this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of perpetuall virginity bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed without the Bishoppe, it is voide. The cauſe was, for that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop was to conſecrate their virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity vnto almighty God. Wherevpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Epiſt. ad Antioch.</hi> thus hee ſpeaketh: <hi>Virgines agnoſcant cui ſeipſas conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt: Let virgins know to whom they have
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1993:12"/> conſecrated themſelues.</hi> The other thing of remarke is, that the eſtate of vowed virginity is better then that of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage: <hi>quod praestantius eſt amplectentes,</hi> Virgins making choice of that which is more excellent. Are theſe docu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſutable to the Proteſtants Theologie? or rather Carnalitie?</p>
            <p>The eight point toucheth the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed <hi>Diſcipline</hi> of the Church, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning faſting vpon certaine dayes, of which <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> maketh mention <hi>Epiſt. ad Philip.</hi> namely of the faſt of Lent, of Wedneſday and Fryday. Is this alſo, I pray you, conformable to the doctrine and practice of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, who refuſe to bee tyed by any ſuch obligation; yea who ſeeke in thoſe ſeaſons, meanes of ſecret eating, and of barrocadoes, to auoyd the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty of ſuch preſcribed faſts, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of Lent?</p>
            <p>The ninth point comprizeth the Catholick doctrine of <hi>VVorth,</hi> or <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:1993:12"/> in good workes, and alſo in thoſe particulerly, as are tearmed by vs <hi>Counſailes,</hi> not commaunded in the Scriptures, hauing in them a peculiar valew in the judgment of Almighty God. To which purpoſe intreating of perpetuall and vowed virginity, <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> auoucheth <hi>Epiſt. ad Phila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delp.</hi> that virgins made acceptance, of that kind of life which is better then the eſtate of marriage: <hi>Quod prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantius eſt amplectentes: Imbracing that which is better. Ep. ad Heronem.</hi> hee vſeth theſe words: <hi>Virgines ſerua, ut praetio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa Chriſti monilia. Guarde well the uir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, as the pretious iewells of Chriſt.</hi> Againe. <hi>Ep. ad Tarſen. Eas que in virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitate degunt in praetio habete, veluti Chriſti Sacerdotes: viduas in pudicitia permanen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, vt altare Dei. Make you great recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of ſuch women as liue in virginity, as it were the Prieſtes of Chriſt: alſo of wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes perſisting in modeſty, as the Altars of God,</hi> Accordingly. Cypr. ep. ad Virgin,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:1993:13"/> calleth vowed Virgins, <hi>The flowers of the Chriſtian flocke.</hi> Is not all this wholly contrary to Proteſtants, who make all workes of vertue equall, &amp; all indifferently, through the corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of Nature, mortall ſinnes, and worthy of eternall damnation? To which foule doctrine they adde two blaſphemies: one that the holy Ghoſt by his Grace ſtirreth vppe theſe workes in men: the other that God in heauen is to giue them a reward.</p>
            <p>The tenth point reſpecteth the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture &amp; effect of <hi>Iuſtificatio,</hi> which is to abolish our cleane the ſpots of ſinnes, before found in the Soule. Of which <hi>S. Ignatius Ep. ad Rom.</hi> thus writeth: <hi>Per dentes beſtiarum molar, vt panis mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus Dei inueniar. I shall be grinded by the teeth of the Lyons, to the end I bee found pure breade of almighty God.</hi> By which words he mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that Charity in Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome should purifie him from all ſtaines of Sinne, &amp; preſent him as
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:1993:13"/> moſt white breade, acceptable vnto the diuine eyes of Almighty God, &amp; conſequently as an obiect paſſing gratious and amiable vnto his will and affection. With which doctrine Proteſtants are at defiance, determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that Juſtification taketh not away Sinnes in the Soule, but only excuſeth them, that although remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, for Chriſt his ſake they bee not imputed.</p>
            <p>The Eleuenth pointe belongeth to Honour by vs to be performed to Saintes: aboute which cuſtome of piety we may vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the doctrine of <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> by the actio of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full preſently performed after his martyrdome, and tranſlation of his reliques from <hi>Rome</hi> to <hi>Antioch. S. Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome ſerm. de S. Ignatio</hi> reporteth, That by the faithfull, his Reliques were repayred vnto, as to <hi>a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall treaſury. Sanctis ad ſe accedentibus benedicens, fiducia &amp; ſtrenua alacritate,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1993:14"/> magnaque fortitudine remittit domum. Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que non hodie tantum, ſed quotidie conflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, ſpirituales ex eo fructus percipientes. Quiſquis enim ad illum cum fide accedit, magnis afficitur beneficijs. Sanctorum enim non modo corpora, ſed &amp; loculi, &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numenta ſpirituali gratia conferta ſunt. Hee bleſsing all that come to him, ſendeth them home replenished with great alacrity and fortitude. VVherevpon not onely to day, but euery day, wee come to his tombe, receyuing thereby ſpirituall commodities. VVhoſoeuer cometh to him with faith, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded with great benefites. For not onely the bodies of Satncts, but their Coffins alſo, and Sepulchers are replenished with ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall grace.</hi> No doubt but <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> in his life conſorred with theſe pious perſons, and with himſelfe in glory, both in doctrine and action. For <hi>S. Augustine lib. 20 cont Fauſt. Cap. 27.</hi> maketh <hi>Manichee</hi> that Arch-heretick the firſt that denyed veneration to the Reliques of Saintes. Is this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:1993:14"/> to the doctrine &amp; cuſtome of Proteſtants and Puritans?</p>
            <p>The twelfth point deſigneth the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of ſinne.</hi> Of which Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts &amp; Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans determine, that it is performed by neceſſity of the will, without free conſent. Wherevpon doth it euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly follow, that God, Authour of that neceſiity, is alſo Author of Sinne. To which blaſphemous doctrine <hi>S. Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> hath declared himſelfe an vtter enemy. And for that purpoſe ſeing certaine Heretiks, as <hi>Nicolaites,</hi> and <hi>Baſilidia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,</hi> teaching a neceſſity of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting all manner of wickednes, hee <hi>Ep. ad Trall.</hi> doth inueigh moſt bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly againſt them, and willeth all good Catholik Chriſtians to auoid them. But eſpecially amongeſt other Heretickes, of whom <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> gaue notice vnto the Church, and whom with deteſtation he rebuked, were <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilides &amp; Carpocras</hi> Princes of the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thariſts,</hi> that is Puritans, in the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:1993:15"/> Church; who, concerning Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence contayned in the frailtie of mans diſordinate nature, through originiall ſinne, broached forth two hereſies: one, that by vertue of a diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne precept, man was bound to yield conſent vnto Concupiſcence. To which purpoſe that Proteſtants may vnderſtand, how loathſome Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, and filthie companions haue alledged Scripture to ſupport their foule and erroneous doctrines, <hi>Carpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cras</hi> cited this text of our Sauiour his owne wordes <hi>Matth. 5. Luke 12. Be thou agreeable quickly to thy aduerſary, whileſt thou art in the way with him, leaſt perhaps thy aduerſary giue thee ouer to the Iudge, and the Iudge commit thee to the Miniſter, and bee caſt into priſon. Clem. Alex. 3. ſtrom.</hi> The other Hereſie enſued hee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reon, to wit, that no conſent or yeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to concupiſcence, did endom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage a beleeuer, either in regard of the preſent eſtate of his iuſtice, or fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:1993:15"/> guerdon in Heauen <hi>Clem Alex. 4. Strom.</hi> With which Puritanicall <hi>Baſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lides</hi> and <hi>Carpocras,</hi> Proteſtants doe accord, in the ſecond Hereſy. For they teach with <hi>Luther &amp; Caluin, (Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Ep. ad Gal Caluin. 2. Inſt. Cap. 16. n. 18. ) that no conſent of will to inward Concupiſcence depriueth a true beleeuer of his now poſseſſed grace of Iuſtification, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned by the ſole act of fayth remayning; or if it do, yet that ſuch a loſſe is onely but for a tyme to endure, in that, as aſſuredly as God raigneth in Heauen, before the moment of death, the ſelfe ſame Iuſtice is to returne to the Soule. VVhitaker lib. 1. &amp; 2. de peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat-origin.</hi> So that in reckoning of Heauenly bliſſe, no wickednes of concupiſcence by their verdicts is domageable. Seing then <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> was a profeſſed enemy of theſe Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hereticks, how could he accord with Proteſtants, who conſort with ſuch damned miſcreants, reproached, and reproued by his writings, &amp; that not
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:1993:16"/> long before his Martyrdome, being then in his way the Roman Theater, and extreamely burning with deſire to encounter with the beaſts of that place, and become for Chriſt his ſake refined Manchet in their mouthes.</p>
            <p>The laſt point importeth, that it belongeth to <hi>Featlye</hi> to proue, that <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> held a contrary doctrine to <hi>S. Policarp,</hi> to <hi>S. Iuſtin</hi> the Martyr, and to ſuch Doctours as florished in the ſecond hundred yeares, after Chriſt: w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> thing as it is impoſſible for him to performe; ſo is more manifeſt and reproachfull his aſſertion, that <hi>S. Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius</hi> was a Proteſtant, or a Puritan.</p>
            <p>Aſſuredly <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> in all points was ſo perfect a Romaine Catholike, that if now according to his profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in the Primitiue Church, hee should liue, &amp; practice in England, as being ſent thither by <hi>S. Peter,</hi> our late Parlamentarians, in their tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous humours, ſo cruelly diſpoſed
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:1993:16"/> againſt the Church of God, would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteed of lyons in <hi>Traian</hi> his Theater in Rome, find out Butchers at <hi>Tyburne</hi> to cut him in peeces.</p>
            <p>Wherefore Reuerend Fathers, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce with you, that you haue ſuch Aduerſaries, who be the vowed ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of Truth, who be, as ſpeaketh <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> of ſome, rather <hi>Chriſtempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri quam Chriſtiani. Ep. ad Trallenſ.</hi> that is, rather Chriſtetymers, then Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. Neither neede I informe you about their manner of proceeding in the cauſe of Theology, or encourage you to continue in your Combat againſt them; in that your learning for the one, and your knowne zeale for the other, neede no ſupporte from my writings or informations. Onely this I haue endighted to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue a ſcandall raiſed by <hi>Featlye,</hi> and in this quarrell to ioyne with you. Hoping that as nowe we bee Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>battants againſt the enemies of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:1993:17"/> God; ſo shall wee one day in his preſence, and Court enioy him, and the fellowship of one another. In the meane ſeaſon I remayne moſt entyrely affected to both your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and yours</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>In Chriſt IESVS, ED. WESTON.</signed>
               <dateline>From Bruges <date>this preſent Feaſt of S. Iames the Apoſtle. 1624.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:1993:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
